2nd Battalion, September 1939-April 1946

I was asked to write a brief history of the Battalion between September 1939 and April 1946 so here it is. Of excuses I have many, and apologies even more, but I would ask you, the reader, to bear with me if this is full of mistakes as I feel sure must be the case. It is unfortunate, but time does not permit that I should study the official Battalion records at the War House, and I regret to say that the records available to me here overseas are far from complete and very sketchy indeed in places.

At the beginning of the war, under the command of Lieut.-Colonel A. E. Stokes-Roberts, M.C., with Major J. P. Fowler-Esson, M.C., as 2nd in Command, the Battalion sailed for France. Until February 1940 we spent our time digging field works and extensions to the Gort Line near Bachy. Some time during this period we did a tour of the Maginot Line, but to my disappointment our records do not show exactly when this was. During December we said good-bye to our Commanding Officer and in January 1940 Lieut.-Colonel P. H. Cadoux-Hudson, M.C., took over command.

Later we had a period of training at Templeuve, mainly on withdrawal, which was to stand us in such good stead later, and stayed there until the attack on Belgium, when we moved forward to the River Dyle, near Louvaine, in positions behind the Belgians. Then came the break-through which was so disastrous to France. On the right flank of the Brigade (1st Guards Brigade) the line was penetrated and we were forced to withdraw in a series of hops back as far as Estoumberg. Here we stayed for five days, only to withdraw again to a canal in front of Roubaix for four days. Thence back again to our last defensive battle line just forward of Uxem, with orders to hold the canal there for at least four days. Finally, out through Dunkirk.

The Battalion began to concentrate in Wakefield, and we were immediately re-equipped, and ready, with orders issued for the re-embarkation for France. During the next few months Major J . P. Fowler-Esson, M.C., left to form 9 Battalion and Major J. M. Lee took over 2nd in Command and later command, when Lieut.-Colonel P. H. Cadoux-Hudson left to take up an appointment as Brigade Commander.

At the end of June 1940 we took over the defences of part of the East Coast in the area of Maplethorpe. We stayed here until the threat of invasion had, for the time being, passed, and in November we moved a little further inland to Louth and Market Rasen, training hard until mid-May 1941. After a series of shifts we found ourselves in Scotland at Inverary, training for assault across the open seas. The months went swiftly past until in March 1942 we found ourselves in Forfar. Not for long were we allowed to stay there, however, as in April we moved to a home area at Shanklin.

One day, I suppose, the story behind that move will be told, but it must suffice that all I can say is that rumour was very strong in the direction of a cross-Channel trip, a short battle and out again. Nothing on those lines occurred and we found ourselves back in Forfar in May 1942 for further extensive training. Yet another period came to an end when in October we received orders for overseas duty. On November 11th we sailed from Liverpool for an unknown destination.

Tebourba Gap

Sea and more sea, then past the Rock and into the port of Algiers, which appeared to be only slightly damaged. From the port we marched to Maison Carre on November 22nd. Thence by rail and road to Tebourba, coming under command 11th Infantry Brigade. Here, as is now well known, the Battalion's first and probably their most brilliant, action was fought under command of Lieut.-Colonel J. M. Lee. Many were our casualties and many the great deeds of valour, and it was here that Major H . W. Le Patourel, V.C., earned that greatest award for gallantry. After the battle the command of the Battalion devolved upon the late Captain J. W. Brehaut, M.C.

The New Year saw us in defensive positions in Munchar and the month was spent quietly. On January 15th, 1943, the Battalion was visited by the G.O.C.-in-C., 1st Army- Lieut.-General K. A. N. Anderson, C.B., M.C. - who presented decorations to several Officers and men. Later in the month the Battalion welcomed Major A. M. Stern as 2nd in Command and the following day Major S. J. Martin was posted to command from 5th Battalion. February found many changes going on and we passed from one command to another. Visiting, or passing through is perhaps a more accurate way of putting it, several places in the process, we finally joined 128 Infantry Brigade in our old area at Munchar. The next few weeks were spent again in comparative quiet, although Battalion H.Q. engaged the attention of the Hun artillery for a few days, much to the discomfort of the occupants.

In March, back under command 1st Guards Brigade, we took up defensive positions at Sbiba. Whilst here the break-through at Kasserine Pass occurred and we were whipped off to restore the area. On the journey we were dive-bombed and lost several vehicles carrying Mk. VII mines with a very noisy explosion.

The final phases of the battle in North Africa then started and the Battalion was again moved from command to command, taking part in attacks with 38th, 12th, 2nd and 10th Infantry Brigades, finishing up with the defensive battle at Gab Gab Gap on May 4th. Then, finally, to 128 Infantry Brigade on May 10th into reserve to follow and mop up, taking thousands of prisoners on the way.

The Victory Parade on May 20th, a most impressive ceremony, started a new period for the Battalion of hard training for the assault landings on the beaches of Salerno.

During the next month we were concentrated at Djidjelli and spent many hours hopping in and out of L.C.I.'s. We all enjoyed a vast amount of swimming in water which was only just cool enough to be refreshing. We said good-bye early in July to Major A. M. Stern and welcomed Major B. P. Doughty-Wylie as 2nd in Command and very shortly afterwards Major P. D. Miller, C.B.E., was posted and was appointed 2nd in Command, Major B. P. Doughty-Wylie taking over command of W Company. Now for our sea legs. On August 11th we embarked at Bougie for Rizerte. Here we carried out the final training for the landing, and waterproofed our vehicles. Embarking on L.S.T.'s on September 5th, and turning our backs on North Africa, we made our way to Italy. Thus ended another period in our history.

Books have been, and more will be, written on the epic battle of Salerno, so I will say little of it except that we had a very uncomfortable first 48 hours on the beaches. After that, fighting became more normal, though the opposition to the advance was fanatical, and by the time we reached Fornace we had had casualties amounting to ten Officers and 294 O.R.'s. Majors D. D. Crofts and V. D. K. Phillips were both killed in action.

Whilst the Battalion was resting at Fornace the front moved forward to Naples and beyond. The Volturno was the next obstacle in our path which we crossed on October 13th behind the 1/4th Battalion unopposed. Within an hour of crossing, however, we were engaged very heavily, the fighting became obscure and fluid, and it was not until late into the afternoon that the final counter-attack was driven off. The next fourteen days saw us involved in some very bitter fighting in the area just north of the river. The canals were annoying to say the least, and tested the swimming ability of many men before we finally achieved a crossing, only to be relieved by 7th Armoured Division that night who remained south of the canal.

On November 6th we said good-bye to Lieut.-Colonel S. J. Martin, and Major P. D. Miller, O.B.E., took over command of the Battalion. During the week that followed we welcomed Major T. A. Rotherham, M.C., who became 2nd in Command. The rest of November and December was spent in positions on the Garigliano and in training for the crossing of it on the Volturno. On January 20th an unsuccessful attempt was made to cross, during which practically the whole of Y Company were taken prisoners.

At the end of February Lieut.-Colonel P. D. Miller left the Battalion and Major T. A. Rotherham, M.C., took over command. Early in March we were pulled out for a long rest and went to Egypt. Training was the order of the day.

April was spent in Palestine, May and most of June in Syria, and on June 27th we embarked at Alexandria for Italy again. August 25th found us back in action near San Ippolito. The start of the break through of the Gothic Line boded well, and by the time we were pulled out for a rest on September 7th, some fifteen miles had been covered against very little opposition except on the crossing of the River Foglia which was very heavily defended.

September 15th proved a difficult day in putting ourselves out to the ridges of Monte Scudo and Monte Colombo, but we were soon relieved by 10 Ind. Division. Water again played the "bogey man" in the form of River Fiumicino where opposition to the advance on Montegallo was very heavy. October 7th, 8th and 9th were very costly in personnel and when the 16th D.L.I. relieved us at 20.30 hours on September 9th we were in a sorry state and sat down at Verruchio for several days to lick our wounds, rest and train. During those critical three days at least one Lance-Corporal learnt what it was like to become Adjutant on the field of battle. The Div. Commander, the late Major-General J. L. I. Hawkesworth, C.B., C.B.E., D.S.O., talked to the Battalion and congratulated them on the magnificent work done in crossing the Fiumicino. Early in November the advance continued up to the Lamone and only on two days was the fighting very heavy, but during the whole period the shelling was the most accurate we had yet encountered.

Lamone Crossing

Now came an epic battle of which little, I think, has yet been written-the crossing of the Lamone and assault on to the heights beyond. After much strong patrolling before H-Hour on D-Day by the carrier platoon and battle patrol the time arrived for us to cross. The task allotted to us was to cross the river and seize a bridgehead 200 yards wide, 300 yards deep, by 20.30 hours, with two Companies to go on through and capture the hill feature known as "Jeremy." The first part of the bridgehead was taken and consolidated nicely on schedule by the carrier platoon, but the battle patrol met heavy opposition and was helped in the task by X Company, and it was not until 03.00 hours the next morning that the bridgehead was finally secured. At 01.00 hours Y and Z Companies passed through on their way to assault Jeremy where those two Companies fought their hardest battle since Salerno. Here was a two-Company-up attack with both Companies pinned to the ground by accurate machine-gun fire from three sides. By 04.00 hours the two Companies, now both very weak indeed, had secured only half their objective. Since W Company had been disbanded some long time before, all three Rifle Companies and Support Company were now committed.

Until daylight the Huns sat upon the tree tops doing heavy damage with their M.G. 42's. By now we were so weak in man power that if a counter-attack came we could only hope to hold isolated positions. During the day a Company of 5 Battalion tried to pass through and relieve the pressure, but after advancing 100 yards they were met by heavy tank and machine-gun fire and were thus pinned and finally forced to withdraw to better positions. For the two days that followed we were subjected to repeated counter-attacks, but managed, by the grace of God, to hold on to our hard-won ground. Now relief came in the form of an attack from the right. December 3rd, 4th, 5th and 6th will be remembered by all who took part in this battle as black yet glorious days.

Now for a well-earned rest. December 15th saw us resting, and before long we were in Greece. Here the Battalion spent much time in patrolling, but somehow managed to enjoy themselves to no small extent, and it was with many regrets that we embarked again for Italy on April 19th, 1945. We had had our last action, but did not know it, so by the time we reached Forli the war in Italy was over, and it was here that we celebrated VE-Day. So ended another period of our history.

May 15th saw us suddenly on the move for Austria, and our first call was in Bezirke of Wolfesberg, with Battalion H.Q., H.Q. and Z Companies at St. Andra, two Companies at St. Paul and one at St. Geogen. Here we stayed until July 30th on occupational and patrol duties, collecting up the Nazis remaining in the area, and generally clearing the countryside of war materials. Minden Day, and we were on the move, so our first opportunity of spending it in a traditional manner had to go by the board. Graz was our next resting place, but to our horror we had not even managed to get all the vehicles in before we were informed that we would move again the next day. Thus onward, following up thc withdrawal of the Russian Armies, and into Friedberg. The Signal Section proved their capabilities on VJ-Day by lighting the square much to the amazement of the local population who did not realise quite what all the fuss was about. However, they were delighted to see a Rugby melee, expressing the exuberance we all felt. They thawed at last and joined in the general jollifications which followed. Lieut.-Colonel T. A. Rotherham, D.S.O., M.C., left us on release early in August and command of the Battalion devolved upon Major W. Spencer (East Yorks).

September saw us move again to Bad Gleichenberg, and in October we welcomed Lieut.-Colonel J. P. Fowler-Esson, D.S.O., M.C., to command the Battalion. December, Christmas and the New Year were spent in Vienna and everyone enjoyed themselves to the full, particularly our commander, whose wife arrived in the country just before Christmas, and we welcome her to the Battalion and hope that she finds Austria as pleasant a country as do most of the rest of us.

January 10th, now back in Bad Gleichenberg, we welcomed Major J. H. Dyas as 2nd in Command, but at the same time we were sorry to learn of the impending disbandment of the 5th Battalion. Thus we came to our present abode, though widely dispersed. Pollau, our centre, is an old-world village set in beautiful countryside, with the peaceful occupation of farming covering the small amount of flat land there is available. The old churches of the village and on the hills around add a majesty to this setting.

May I finally apologise for any mistakes I may have made and at the same time invite now released members of the Battalion to write articles to fill out my very disjointed story.

Times and men change, and so that readers may be able to locate some of those they knew I have shown a list of the Battalion Officers as they were on VE-Day and also on April 1st this year.

E. B. Newcomb, Captain.

From Hampshire Regiment Journal, May 1946